hello everyone
welcome to the active inference lab this
is the first active inference model
stream active inference model stream 1.0
and i'm really excited for today's
conversation i'm
daniel friedman and just to introduce
the other participants today
uh ryan go for it uh yep
hi i'm uh ryan uh i'm from the florida
institute of brain research
hi i'm christopher i'm a phd student at
the mrc
cognition brain sciences unit which is
based at the university of cambridge
hi i'm max murphy i just completed my
phd at university of kansas in
bioengineering
uh with a focus on neural engineering
awesome
thank you everyone for participating and
for ryan and christopher
two of the authors of this awesome work
we're going to be exploring
so this is the first in a several part
series that is going to be highlighting
several perspectives and
addressing questions related to the
active inference tutorial paper
of smith at all called a step-by-step
tutorial
on active inference and its applications
to empirical data
so the idea here is for those who are
working with empirical data
to learn about active inference as a
method and also for those in the active
inference community to be learning about
some of the methods that apply
active inference if you're listening
you're participating
and if you have any questions during the
live stream feel free to post it
in the youtube live chat and we'll try
to address it during
or after this presentation that we're
about to get
if you have questions after the live
stream please feel free to leave it
in a comment form and we'll try to
address it
and integrate your input in future
sessions
and to learn more and to participate
check out activeinference.org or any of
the information in the video's
description
so that's all the information uh or
metadata for this video
the way this is gonna work today is
we're going to do some introductory
questions uh just sort of like asking
what in general is this work about
what motivated the authors to write the
paper the way that they did
and then both ryan and christopher are
going to share their screens
for part of the presentation and they're
going to show us a few different things
about the work that they've done and
then we have a couple of questions
prepared on our side
but also we're going to be looking at a
live chat if anyone has questions so
just post it
whenever you feel like it in the live
chat and then we'll again try to address
it
so as i stated the intro questions and
then we'll go to the presentations
so first intro question to uh the
authors
is what is this work what is exciting
about it what
motivated you to work on it
um okay so uh so just to kind of
reintroduce myself a little bit more so
i'm uh ryan smith so i'm an investigator
at the laureate institute for brain
research in tulsa oklahoma
and the um the focus of our institute is
um primarily on uh neuroimaging
and sort of neuroscience approaches to
understanding
um psychology and psychiatry with a
focus on sort of treating psychiatric
disorders
um and so for a while now there has been
um the use of simpler computational
models
primarily reinforcement learning models
or drift diffusion models things like
that
um out there for researchers for who are
working with empirical data
who so there are good resources out
there for people to learn those methods
um to apply them to data in their own
research
um however at the moment so active
inference is a sort of much newer field
especially it's sort of a formulation in
terms of uh
partially observable markov decision
processes and
there isn't really to date a really
clear sort of combined place
to learn the sort of practical methods
to um to build these sorts of models
and um to then sort of apply them
to uh task behavior in empirical studies
um so the kind of motivation for this
paper this tutorial
was to allow somebody you know so new
students or somebody who's sort of like
an early
earlier you know junior faculty things
like that who wants to
go in this direction to give them the
resources they need to do that
as easily as you know and as thoroughly
as possible so
even if you start out not really
having any background in this stuff the
hope was
that you know the the first section of
the paper would
allow you to kind of get enough of a
background in theory
such that you would understand how to
then learn how to build these models
specifically for empirical tasks and
eventually
to learn how to fit those models to uh
to data
um so that they could be used in your
own sort of research
um you know even you know for across
many different
fields so i would say what's what's
exciting or motivating is
is primarily just that if you're a new
researcher and you're interested in this
but you don't know how to do it
you know the hope is is kind of going to
be like a one-stop shop where if you can
get beginning to end then you'll
know how to do what you need to do to
start using it in your own research
so that's the major driving uh
motivation
awesome i love that one stop shop for a
researcher who wants to apply the
methods but doesn't really know
where to start so that's really a great
idea and
you have version the document many times
to really
address people's input so it's cool how
it's an evolving document as well
so christopher what would you say in
response to those
intro questions um
so i think there are two parts of my
motivation for writing this the first
was the selfish motivation in that i
think
if you want to understand something the
best way to do it is actually to write a
tutorial on it
and so in when ryan asked me to do this
tutorial with him
i was jumped at the opportunity just
because it would be an opportunity to
kind of
actually learn this stuff better myself
and really get into some of the more
technical details
um and so then more broadly speaking
though
i think there are lots if in principle
there's nothing kind of
applying these models in practice is no
more complicated than doing like
model-based reinforcement learning
and yet it's incredibly more common to
see researchers working with
various more sophisticated rl schemes
and i think
if you are a graduate student maybe
starting in psychology or neuroscience
you're like hey i'm
interested in whatever it is uh decision
making under uncertainty
and i mean we have a finite time in this
earth right and a fine amount of time to
actually
dedicate into learning things and so i
think it would be perfectly rational if
it's someone to look at active inference
research
like wow this is super technical i wish
i could learn it but here's this other
thing where i can go on euromatch i can
read sutton and barto
and really totally get up scratch and
use my research fairly easily
and there just wasn't something really
accessible
to help people actually apply in their
own research um so that was kind of my
yeah yeah i mean i should say just as a
little background you know when i wanted
to learn this stuff
originally at the end of my postdoc
before i took my current
faculty position um i the only way to do
it
the only way that i could learn it was
actually to go you know hang out at the
phil
in london with carl for about four
months um
and you know just ask people a ton of
questions and
sit there and that was the only way you
know so without having to
you know physically go to uh one
location in the world i was very far
away from you know my current
institution
and without doing that there really was
no way for me to do it so i mean this is
sort of a out of empathy for my past
self
that you know this is the sort of thing
i wish i would have had available to me
so i could learn this stuff
independently
cool so max um what is your
background or what got you really
excited to work through the paper and
develop a lot of the examples out on
your own um computer and everything so
what what got you excited or where are
you coming from today
sure um yeah so uh maybe i'm kind of
your target demographic in some sense
uh i don't know that i could really be
considered a junior investigator
although i hope i could someday be that
um and i'm interested in um i'm much
more on the
the motor motor system side of
neuroscience as opposed to the decision
making so this
just the whole um lexicon it's a little
different
but i am seeing so many commonalities
when i'm coming from a signal processing
background i think of things
um in terms of kalman formulation and
trying to integrate sensory and motor
information i see a lot of similarities
there and so for somebody like
myself then looking at some of fristen's
work and seeing how
he's described you know the the anatomy
of uh
inference and could this apply also in
motor systems
i'm very interested to see how this
might apply in my
own future research and work
cool so let's just say that you were
speaking
ryan first and then christopher to that
early
investigator researcher of any age who
is like okay
i get it um in reinforcement learning
it's about reward or reward-centric
learning is about reward
what is active inference how is it
taking a different
perspective on what it is that organisms
are doing than
that kind of classical account of reward
based learning for example or whatever
you'd like to contrast it with
but what is the bridge from the kind of
assumptions
and implications that lead somebody to
work on that classical framing
versus what is the um difference in
thinking that is active inference and
how is that manifested in the model
so i think this is actually a really
important thing to bring up right from
the start
is that so there's a there's a kind of
big distinction between
um when people talk about the free
energy principle broadly or the
philosophy of the free energy principle
and there's a very kind of uh you know
somewhat wide chasm between that
and what gets called active inference
nowadays where active inference is a
corollary
of the free energy principle but um
you know active inference as formulated
in terms of partially observable
partially observable markov decision
processes is a
quite a bit narrower right it's a very
specific sort of
discrete state-space generative model um
and that has particular sorts of
elements to it um
and it it doesn't actually require
knowing a lot of the things that people
talk about with respect to the free
energy principle more broadly
um it appeals to um free energy and
expected free energy
as functions right as more or less cost
functions for
figuring out what the best choice to
make is um
and it but but at the end of the day i
mean when you apply
these sorts of models to behavioral
tasks that they used in studies
it's actually there's quite a bit of
similarity i mean you can really see
active inference models or at least the
mdp formulation
as as just a particular is kind of like
what chris said is just a particular
kind of flavor almost of model based
reinforcement learning
um you know so instead of i mean there's
there's some sort of technical
differences
right where um the way that sort of carl
and them have set it up
what you're doing is kind of like it
allows for kind of a fully unified
bayesian way of doing
reinforcement learning and decision
making processes
and you do that by instead of calling
something
a reward per se you define this
probability distribution
over observations that gets called a
preference distribution
and so reward then becomes a kind of
probabilistic preference
to observe some things over others um
you know so if you call
a particular observation a reward um
then calling it a roar just amounts to
having a
precise preference distribution that has
a precise
high value over whatever that rewarding
outcome is
and then the agent is simply driven to
make decisions that it thinks is most
likely
to get it to observe the thing it
prefers
right so this preference distribution is
more or less a way of specifying what is
rewarding to the agent right what the
agent is seeking
um one thing that is kind of nice about
active inference that's a little
different
from reinforcement learning per se
or there's a few things i should say one
is that um
making decisions based on trying to
minimize expected free energy which
chris will cover
doesn't just try to maximize reward
it also simultaneously tries to maximize
information gain
so so what will happen is you know say
say an agent starts out in a dark room
you know just to take a very kind of
contentious
you know philosophy of the fep sort of
example
right say an agent starts out in a dark
room um
which means that it doesn't know where
anything is
right so that means it has a lot of
uncertainty over what state it's in
um and let's say simultaneously in
another room
there's a fridge with some food in it um
then there will be two different sorts
of drives there right there'll be this
epistemic drive
to do whatever it thinks is gonna give
it the most information gain
right which will be go turn on the light
right so then it'll know
what state it's in right whether it's in
room a or room b
right or whether there's a couch in the
room or whether there's a
tv in the room or whatever right um and
that's not
reward per se that's just trying to make
the app
choose the action that's going to
maximize the amount of information you
get
the other the other chunk of it though
is to maximize
observing preferred outcomes and so the
agent will also be driven to just leave
the room
to go to the fridge you know to observe
itself eating food um
you know so in practice what will happen
that typically won't happen
at least in a standard reinforcement
learning setting
is that the agent won't just try to
maximize reward directly
a lot of times it will first choose the
action that will
help it figure out where it is so that
it's more confident what to do
to get the reward later so
so it's so it's really not again in
practice these models are
are just a nice fully bayesian way to
integrate
perception learning and decision making
where decision making is driven to both
maximize information gain and maximize
reward
christopher thanks a lot anything else
to add there
um no not particularly i i think the
only thing i would say and i'm going to
say this in a little bit
on a slide is if you're interested in
the technical details what ryan just
said there are two really good papers
um maybe we can make these slides
available afterwards as well
um one's by norsajid and i'm not sure if
i'm sorry if i'm
butchered your name there um the other
one's lancelot decosta
and they have two excellent papers
comparing it to reinforcement learning
so
formulations excellent um just to draw
out a couple points
ryan from what you said so one is that
uh
the active inference framework and
specifically the
po mdp the partially observable markov
decision process
instantiation of active inference is a
corollary
or like a derivative of the free energy
principle
and there's a lot of philosophy and
contentiousness around different aspects
of that we're going to read a paper in
active inference stream 14 by mel
andrews about
the math is not the territory about the
philosophy and the status so yes if you
want to go
that way there's a whole rabbit hole
there but this is kind of like a tool
like a linear regression
you don't get caught up in the weeds on
number theory or on the information
space that it's about
where the calculation is useful and
tractable
it's going to be a tool so that's kind
of where we're coming at at least today
and in this series another interesting
thing
and in contrast with reinforcement
learning which is kind of like
uh reinforce what works and don't
reinforce what doesn't work that neurons
that fire together wire together
positive reinforcement schemes there is
a reward preference built into that kind
of model
but when there's a basin of low reward
it's often difficult for those models to
latch on
so we saw that in the paper of alec
chance at all
in active inference stream eight scaling
active inference
that kind of showed how even up against
these very very
large scale machine learning models like
q reinforcement learning and things like
that
other state-of-the-art deep learning
models that the active inference
trolley car and control theory robots
were able to work really well because
first they did what you just described
ryan which was
they kind of went into an explore mode
before going into a more fine-tuning
mode and so in doing so they transcended
the explore
exploit simple trade-off it's not just a
knob in this model
it's not a coefficient to balance
explore versus exploit i hope will draw
out an understanding that they're
actually related in a different way
because there's something that's model
based and generative that's happening
and so
really a ton of interesting stuff so at
this point
i would think we could go into the
presentations
if people have any questions that arise
put them in the youtube chat and i'll be
copying those out
for addressing them later and um other
than that let's just work through the
presentations however
ryan and christopher have set up and
preferred
cool okay go ahead and just share your
screen chris you can just go ahead
yeah it's like just kidding
okay so i'm using a dual monitor setup
we'll see how this goes
um
okay sorry i now have to open system
preferences sorry
to allow microsoft teams to use it sorry
about that
um
okay should be with you momentarily
cool
good to digest really it's really
it's interesting stuff and we're all
learning by doing
here so i just really appreciate and
have just seen a lot of
appreciation for this kind of work
because in some ways it's like the
missing
piece between a lot of these
hypothetical or abstract or scaffold
models
or what people have heard about with
respect to what active inference is
and then how it's deployed how it's
enacted so to take the inactivist
insight seriously as practitioners of
science
and as communicators as well it means
making this kind of work and
showing us how you do it as we all are
trying to like
figure out every level from literally
the tech to
the best way to make it rigorous and
accessible
the best ways to talk about it so yeah
what what do you think about that ryan
um yeah i mean i totally agree hold on
to chris
yeah actually i've never used um this
there should be a little thing in the
upright corner it's like an arrow
pointing into us into like a square
share content
are you guys both on pcs yeah
yeah okay so yeah so
it should be upright corner like right
next to the leave button
okay um or ryan you could present
first or yeah um
i actually have a question i i have a
question it will really work for me to
present first i think i think
you know yeah what i'm gonna do not
gonna be so comprehensible before chris
got it i actually have a question that
will take a couple of minutes uh
christopher while you're figuring it out
is
what tools would somebody need to follow
along
so what programming language or what
interface
do they need what background knowledge
do they
need is there a software to download is
there a course
what are the prerequisites for doing
what we're about to basically jump into
um yeah so i mean i'll just say that
that you know a lot of this stuff was
originally designed
by carl fristen um and if you know
a lot about carl um you know before he
proposed a lot of this active inference
stuff you know he
was uh sort of most uh you know famous
or his his biggest contribution was
putting together
uh sp spm within matlab spm is um
like a it's called statistical
parametric mapping software but it was
more or less the original way of doing
fmri so like analyzing functional and
like neuroimaging data
and so a lot of the scripts and dynamic
puzzle modeling i should say which is a
particular sort of approach to doing
your imaging
i mean so a lot of basically all the
standard resources all the standard
coding routines everything
for actually building active inference
models right now
is primarily an spm which runs
within matlab um so and all the
kind of supplementary tutorial code that
we've provided we've provided i think
six
six or seven different um different
supplementary scripts
where you can actually run the
simulations and build these models
yourself
they are they are all they're all in
matlab um
so if you so if you have matlab then you
need to have downloaded spm
um and with matlab and spm you um
you will have everything you need to do
to open our supplementary code
and to uh and to follow along so a lot
of the tutorial is actually set up so
it assumes that you're kind of have the
paper open
side by side with the code so you can
actually click on
you know different options to simulate
and reproduce all the figures in the in
the tutorial paper
so it's uh yeah so the short answer is
you need matlab and you need spm
um thanks for that and you need to have
some minimal
ability to you know work with work with
matlab
just just to piggyback on to that for
anybody's
benefit watching this in the future
whenever you're watching this uh
once you get the spm folder you know
you'll unzip that you'll get that folder
you'll put that somewhere on your
computer
you'll want to make sure that you add
path from your matlab workspace when
you're in the supplementary code
provided
by uh ryan and christopher
when you're in that workspace add path
of that folder wherever you put it
add path of that folder slash
toolbox slash dem
and then you should have access to the
additional spm12
scripts that you need in order to make
use of the functions they've provided
yeah no thank you very much i mean
that's that yeah for someone who's never
used matlab yes there's a few
steps like that which are super
important um
yeah because basically all these scripts
are actually within yeah within
the dem toolbox um
of spm um and uh all the scripts they've
provided
um call on uh sort of
sub functions um within that are within
spm
um so so yeah it won't unfortunately
uh none of them will work without
without spm at the moment
um although there are certainly efforts
to try to make
um some of these routines more sort of
generally accessible
and like free software um like alec alec
chance for example
is in the process of um i think writing
a uh like a python
version of the um of the main um
active inference uh mdp script which is
called the
it's called uh uh spm
underscore mdp underscore vb underscore
x
and that just corresponds that just mdp
underscore vb underscore x corresponds
to markov decision process
underscore variational base underscore x
which stands for factorized
um and i'll i'll go over what
factorization is
um and how you actually code that in
once we get to
my section um
okay i'm gonna ask a follow-up there so
i have my
desktop computer i have matlab and it's
all working with referencing
spm most updated version
and i've run through the examples that
we're going to be working through maybe
today or the ones that are in the paper
so i kind of hit enter and i got things
to work
everything's all the scripts are working
fine
what information from my system do i
need to know
like what measurements are going to be
relevant for me to bring to the table
if i'm going to do a t-test for whether
two ant colonies are
a different uh size you know i know what
kind of machinery i'm going to need you
know two columns
in the excel spreadsheet or something
but what kind of data
or what attributes of the system are
important
to bring to the table for an
investigator to utilize
the examples that you're providing
um yeah so i mean so i mean there's a
couple things i mean so
so first the um
you know so the first goal is you know
you take a particular
behavioral task and you have to figure
out
what the right generative model is um
for that task
um and this is the sort of thing that
i'll give an example of i can actually
show you multiple examples of this
um and so once you have this or
generative model set up
then you can run simulations and those
simulations will generate
observations and they'll generate
expected actions um
so so what you need then is you need
data
from an actual participant performing
that task where you'll know
on each trial um what the person
observed right what the tasks amelia
were
and you'll know what action they
actually chose
and so then what you'll do ultimately is
you'll do what's called parameter
estimation
which is and again this will be a lot
more comprehensible
once i actually show you but but
basically what you try to do
is you try to find the set of parameter
values in the model
that generates behavior that's most
similar to what the participant actually
did
and so once you find the parameters you
know say one has a value of two and the
other has a value of four
and that generates behavior that's
identical to whatever a given
participant did
then those values of 2 and 4 you can use
those
as individual difference estimates you
know so if you have those values for a
bunch of different people who behaved in
different ways on the task
then you could say hey you know is there
something different right about the
people that have a parameter value of
four
versus a parameter value of eight right
can i use that to predict for example
you know how well somebody's going to
respond to a particular treatment
in in computational psychiatry um
um hi chris twice yes
um
yeah but so but so but so that's that's
kind of the idea
um you know and i mean i can't i can
share my screen in the meantime
um i don't know well here i can i can
perhaps go through
some of this um so i'll just share my
screen until
i'm good yeah sorry that was this whole
thing was
um oh you're good okay
i think i am at least can you guys see
my screen uh yes perfect
uh right here okay great sorry about
that there was some a whole bunch of
privacy issues
um they had to enjoy the passwords there
anyway
okay we are here so
okay so are you guys seeing my present
of you or are you seeing the full thing
looks uh we see the we see the full
slide yeah just the slope awesome
okay so this is just kind of part one um
after i've done
gone through this uh ryan's going to
take over and go through some of the
practical aspects of it
um and so then just kind of reiterate
the scope and purpose
our target audience really is kind of
researchers in neuroscience and
psychology that don't have a strong
kind of quantitative background in maths
or ml in particular early career
researchers
and we just really want to provide
people with a requisite background
to actually apply this in the context of
their own
okay and then so just to quickly
highlight some really fantastic other
resources
um the first paper is by lancelot de
costa which is an incredible technical
review
just came out mathematical psychology um
north has a really
other incredible paper this came out
neural computation
and i think the um comparison to
dynamic programming and bellman
formulations um is still in pre-print if
that's right ryan um but as well there's
some really phenomenal
informal tutorials with oleg solo shock
i'm sorry if i butchered your name but
anyway they're
fantastic kind of informal tutorials on
medium
and then lastly is kind of the closest
thing to what we're doing today
is these lectures by philip
schwartenbeck
in the computational psychiatry
summer school and these really are
fantastic
the only difference is that they work
with to my knowledge i think they work
with the unfactorized mdp scheme which
is a little less flexible than what
we're working with
um okay and so
there are a lot of ways of kind of
motivating active inference
i think kind of the way that's most
intuitive to a lot of people in
cognitive science or backgrounds in
cognitive sciences to
kind of start from perspective of the
bayesian brain and so
interrupting if anything's kind of
moving too quickly or too slowly or
anything like that but broadly speaking
the idea is
is that the brain encodes a generative
model of the environment
where this generative model is just kind
of a joint probability distribution
and then outside or in the outside world
as it were
there are states and observation states
give rise to observations
and we use the generative model in
combination with bayesian updating
to infer the hidden causes of our
sensations
from the observations and then we take
actions based upon
our kind of internal model of the world
that couples us back
to the generative process that if that
makes sense and so there's this kind of
perception
action loop that's always going on so
chris i think i think you might want to
tell people just what the p o comma
so that is a joint probability
distribution over observations
states and policies where policies are
just actions or sequences of actions
um that are available kind of all of the
actions that
are afforded to the agent essentially um
okay and so then kind of
just we start with like a re illustrate
this we'll just give like a really
really basic example
and so you might be imagine being
presented with
kind of a shadowy shape like this and
then you might and what you want to do
is infer the causes of that shape based
just based upon
the observations but you don't just have
observations right
you have some prior knowledge about the
world
um and so we can specify that here so we
might say
where two possible causes in this very
limited example
there is we might say that the shadow is
caused by a convex surface or a concave
surface
and they have fairly similar prior
probabilities however we also have the
structural prior that we've kind of
acquired through a lifetime experience
of just light emanating from above
and under the kind of a structural pry
that light emanates from above
the likelihood of the observation of
that particular shadow
kind of conditional being concave is
much much higher
okay and so then we can then combine the
two the prior and the likelihood
to give us a joint distribution where
this is just kind of conditional on a
specific observation
we can then and then we sum over
the states in that likelihood to give us
our marginal likelihood and then divide
our joint distribution or our generative
model by our
marginal likelihood and that's called
model inversion or is often
colloquially called model inversion
and from there we get our posterior
distribution this is the probability of
states
conditional on observations and so we
started with a prior
and a likelihood and got to a posterior
through bayes rule and that is kind of
formally speaking the optimal way to
infer
the probability of hidden causes given
observations
and the complication to all this is that
the marginal likelihood is generally
speaking computationally intractable
um so i in the case kind of these very
simple discrete distributions
the number of sums that you have to
perform scales exponentially with the
size of your hypothesis space so that's
extremely impractical um and
kind of more realistically when you're
working with in continuous state spaces
if you have non-gaussian or non-linear
um signals
they're just analytically the
distributions is analytically
interactable
so chris i think i think uh max had a
question yeah yeah sorry
yeah real quick uh just just to really
explicitly uh touch on
the idea of hidden hidden states and
hidden variables
in this particular context uh would it
be fair to say that it's not only
the convexity or concavity of the the
potential
you know thing that i'm looking at but
also i could think of
the light source the direction from
where the light source is as being
another hidden variable
and those things together would it be
fair to term those as under my
markov blanket or is that uh getting a
little too far out from where we want to
be talking right now
yeah so markov blankets don't really the
kind of markup blanket concept here
doesn't really
come in in in any really interesting way
i mean you can formulate it that way but
really the idea is just
you have this prior expectation so when
you're looking at the little gray disc
right there under observation
most people when you look at it even
though it's actually just a flat
shape with some you know it's just a
flat two-dimensional thing that has
a little bit of darkness in one place a
little bit of lightness in another
um you know if most people see that as
being concave
even though it's a flat 2d thing
right so the idea is is just that
there's a reason
right why people typically see it as
being concave as it's kind of like
popping in as opposed to out
and that's specifically because there's
this prior belief
that um that light sources tend to come
from above um so the the hidden states
here
are kind of there is a joint in the
likelihood which just means
that there's a in the upright where it
says likelihood there's a concave comma
light from above right so those are two
different hidden states
what it's saying is um if
the hidden states are concave and light
from above
if the combination of those things is
what's generating
the what i'm seeing with that gray disc
thing
um the probability of the shadow shape
that the shadow pattern that you see um
is 0.9
whereas if it was convex and light from
above if those were the two hidden
states
then the probability you get that shame
that same shadow pattern is only 0.1
right in other words it'd be really hard
to get that
pattern of shading if if the thing was
popping out
under the assumption that light's coming
from above
um so so the observation here is shadow
and the hidden states are
concave and light from a concave or
convex and light from above and like
from below
okay thanks yeah just one other quick
example there would be like the chess
board
with a shadow and a dark square it's
perceived under a deep cultural prior
that chessboards are regular
alternating grids it makes an ambiguous
shaded square appear as something that's
quite different than it is people can
look that up
and then another uh thing this reminds
me of is like using a t-test
to test whether group a versus b is
taller or something like that
it assumes but um it can be an
assumption that can be
slightly bent is it assumes that other
than the variable being considered
other things are sort of fixed or not
mattering otherwise your statistical
test is basically misleading
because it could be capturing some
totally confounding variable
in the framework you put it in and so
whenever you're talking about a real
biological organism you're talking about
conditioning on certain things
and then given what is totally
conditioned out of the picture
so i i kind of see where you're going
with the blanket but it's
not specifically in this place but a
good question
but it's like depending on the
irrelevancies that we can condition out
then we're looking at the conditional
relationships between different
observed states versus the hidden things
so
cool stuff and again in the live chat
people can post any
questions on it continue christopher
yeah thank you
um yeah thanks for covering that ryan um
okay so then the idea is is that the
marginal likelihood is generally
computationally intractable
but kind of borrowing some ideas from
statistical physics
what you can do is actually use some
approximation techniques and instead of
evaluating the marginal likelihood
directly
we can evaluate something that's always
provably greater than or equal to
the marginal likelihood i'm so going
through that
right now okay and so we're just going
to take the logs kind of for
mathematical convenience and the reason
we always work with logs or generally
speaking is because
log log algebra is just a lot easier
just because it turns multiplications
into arithmetic
um so things it's just easier to work
with essentially
so we'll take the negative log of our
marginal likelihood
um this is also sometimes called
bayesian model evidence and
when we have a negative log of a
probability it's also called surprise
and information theory which is kind of
the terminology i'm going to use the
rest of this kind of presentation
and so you can see on the right-hand
side of the equality this
is kind of the sum rule of probability
we can get back our surprise by just
summing over
kind of all of the states under our uh
joint distribution over states and
outcomes
and then we can kind of do a little bit
of a trick here so what i'm going to do
now
or show you is that we are going to
multiply this joint distribution or
generative model by some arbitrary
distribution
we multiply and divide by the same
and so nothing has changed here this
quality still holds
i could cancel these if we wanted to but
i don't want to
and that's in particular because i want
to take advantage of something called
jensen's inequality and that is that a
result showing that the
expectation of a logarithm is always
less than or equal to the logarithm of
an expectation
and so the idea is is that this sum
here where the logarithm is inside this
summation
where sorry so we're taking we're
summing over
this kind of difference between a
generative model
and this approximate or target
distribution
when the logarithm is inside that it is
always going to be and we're in kind of
negative territory
it's always going to be greater than
this quantity on the left-hand side
where this left-hand quantity is equal
to surprise because
the log is outside the sum we can cancel
these kind of approximate distributions
right and end up
back at surprise on the right hand side
we can't do that
this right hand side will only be equal
to surprise
when our generative distribution
perfectly matches our approximate
distribution
and so this quantity on the right hand
side here
this is variational free energy and so
the idea is
is that we find the probability
distribute this approximate probability
distribution which we make simplifying
assumptions about and so we can
kind of evaluate analytically
we make simplifying we find the value of
this distribution
that best minimizes f
where f is variational free energy does
that kind of make sense
hey chris just one thing are you like
trying to like move your mouse around to
point to things
no okay i'm actually putting my mouse
i'm scribbling my mouse a little bit on
the live stream they should be able to
see that
but christopher thank you for that
really awesome
example because it really clarified a
few things
any other notes to add here otherwise
this is cool to continue
yeah okay so then just kind of give a
really toy example of this
so we can define our approximate
posterior
kind of arbitrarily is a flat
distribution we'll have a true posterior
generally speaking we don't know what
this is but for illustration's sake
we're going to give
kind of give it to you and then we can
have a joint distribution
and an observation what the observation
will do is it's just going to select
a kind of a column from this joint
distribution
and so then we have we can now enter
this into the equation we saw on the
last slide
and we'll slowly but surely in each
update
nudge our posterior distribution
such that it minimizes f on each step
and at the third step you see what we
should see is that when f is at a
minimum
it is equal to surprise and when f is at
a minimum as well
it's at a minimum because the true
posterior
and our approximate posterior match
so that kind of makes sense um and so
the idea is is that
by performing bayesian inference and
having and kind of forcing
some arbitrary distribution to
approximate our posterior
we come up with an upper bound on
surprise or we come to
an upper bound on surprise let me kind
of just
walk through and just double check here
so q
of s is our estimate of whether the coin
is a fair coin 50 50 means that it's 50
50 and then 80 20 is the reality
on the table so to speak so it's almost
like
first we click from 50 50 we see heads
come up
and that contributes a little bit of
evidence that maybe heads is more likely
so we go from 50 50 to 60 40.
and then something happens again and we
click on the second update
to 7.7.3 we click eventually to 0.8.2
and then if we click all the way to
point nine point one
so again in 90 10 all of a sudden we go
uh back up from 0.693
back up so if we were to plot this final
estimated f we'd find that we're like
going downhill getting better
get to 0.693 in this discrete 0.1
movement space and then we pop up a
little bit too far we overshoot
and we get a little bit more surprised
by the distributions that we're
drawing yeah exactly that's perfect um
well the only the only thing that i
would say
that's i mean a little different just to
note is that there's nothing in this
example where you observe something over
and over again
this is this is just a single
observation once
and you're trying to figure out what
what is the you're trying to figure out
what the true posterior
is trying to get as close to it as
possible so all you're doing is saying
here's the single observation
and i'm going to try out a bunch of
different values for qs
a bunch of different values for that
approximate distribution
and i'm just going to find the one you
know through this kind of iterative
updating thing where i slowly move qs
you know to different values you just do
that for a single observation
you update until you find the minimum
free energy value which just tells you
that your approximate posterior the qs
thing is as close
is really close to the true posterior
that you couldn't figure out
on your own because the problem was too
tough to solve with exact bayesian
inference
um so this this is kind of corresponds
to what people might talk about as
prediction error minimization
right so you just see this observation
once
and the brain tries to minimize
prediction error by minimizing f
by just moving beliefs until it finds
the
the belief that minimizes f
which is the same thing as minimizing
prediction error
um look at that if that makes sense
let me clarify because i i think that
really helped me understand it and
at first i thought wait with one
observation because at first when i
described it i was thinking update was
tied to a new observation from the coin
but then i thought well if you're only
getting one observation the maximum
likelihood model is a coin that only
comes up heads
because you only have one observation
but it's not one-shot
parameter learning naive it's actually
a a tethered estimate that's tethered
even loosely but non-zero tethering to a
prior
0.5.5 some people will say uninformative
but all priors are informative
they're all what they are and then it's
almost like because of the logs
even though you only observed the coin
come up once it's like all right it's a
little too far to update
to 99 one just from seeing one coin flip
i would need extraordinary evidence for
extraordinary
updates and so it's like that one heads
observation
updates you from 50 50 to near
80 20 which does happen to be close
to the actual probability of the coin
and it also happens to navigate this
explore exploit in an interesting way
because it updates it but not all the
way so it's just kind of showing
how the bayesian updating brings some of
that
wisdom of multi-observation learning
like slow updating of parameters and
uh sequential uh updating to
a little bit of a different context so
yeah i mean
i do want to clarify here a little bit i
mean there's there's no actions here
so there can't really be explore exploit
right you can't
you can't choose to look over here
versus over there to gain information
right so explore exploit is you know
specifically in the realm of making
choosing actions that will minimize
uncertainty
versus maximize reward um this is this
is really more just
with with normal free energy right we're
not too expected free energy yet which
is the decision-making part
with normal free energy there's you can
think the simplest way to think about
um free energy is just in terms of
um complexity minus accuracy
which is equivalently complexity plus
prediction error
and all that all that ultimately means
is so the complexity thing is basically
how much you have to change your beliefs
um so it's basically saying what's the
minimum change in my beliefs that will
make my new beliefs as accurate as
possible right so i have to move my
beliefs as little as possible while also
minimizing prediction error
if that if that makes sense so this what
this generative model is saying is just
that the probability that we're in state
one
is point eight if i were to chew if if i
were to get this observation
where the probability of being in state
two is only point two where to get this
observation
right so so i mean the probably a better
example than the um
than the like heads and tails thing
would just be would just be something
like the concave complex example we gave
before
right there is some possibility where
where light from above
you know where light from below could
cause the shading pattern but it's just
much less likely
right so you're just trying to find the
the belief
right that it's convex and light from
above
that that is the one that most likely
generated what you're what you're seeing
and it might take a bunch of updates
like that given just what you see once
to kind of arrive at the best fitting
belief there's a related question
in the live chat that i'm just gonna ask
because it's on the topic
they asked is this approximate bayesian
inference thing
called something else in stats outside
of active inference or is this unique to
active inference because this isn't
sequential bayesian updating as you
mentioned
this isn't a standard bayesian filter
what is this called outside of the
active inference field
so yeah it's just variational bays
variational bays where does the
partially observable markov decision
process come into play
uh we'll cover that in a moment's time
actually yeah it doesn't
it doesn't yeah it doesn't come in yet
so i think one thing to say is kind of
writing this tutorial it's hard to
please everyone right like in going
through some of the feedback like we get
we got some feedback where people were
just like utterly confused
and wanting clear explanations and then
at the other end of the spectrum we
wanted there were people wanting much
more technical details like how does
this relate to things like gradient
descent
because this is just kind of a very
simplified cartoon example of something
called grading of
a gradient descent scheme where you're
doing a gradient descent
on free energy um and so i would just
say kind of the flag
of these issues is one i would say
if something's unclear in this
presentation read the paper because we
gave things
we cover things a lot more detail in the
paper and if that isn't technical enough
for you
actually go and just look at our code we
supply
a kind of standalone script where we
it's extreme and it's extremely well
commented and from there you should be
able to figure out everything that's
going on
so all of this stuff in this
presentation is kind of necessarily
simplified because you don't
really need those technical details to
kind of start
using the framework or start getting
intuition for how things work
but once you do have an intuition and
you want more just go and see the code
i would say um awesome
it's like you can use the anova package
in our
without going into the source code it's
helpful it's a tool for scientists
and then if you're curious about the
underpinnings of statistics
and perennial philosophical debates
there's a literature
and a search bar but today it's about
the applications of these methods
which is awesome so thanks for everyone
for the questions keep them coming but
this is great
discussion i really appreciate it
okay and so just kind of to recap there
i haven't covered action yet i'm going
to cover action a little bit
but just kind of to recap the idea is
under active inference
organisms are kind of we model them as
if
their phenotype is in their body and
their brain kind of embodies a
generative model of the environment
and organisms kind of invert a generated
model to arrive in
approximate posterior distribution over
the hidden causes of sensory input
and they do this by minimizing
variational free energy
so that should that much should
hopefully be clear by this point
and so then on to the generative model
and it is a very specific type of
generative model
namely it's a partially observable
markov decision process
and so there's kind of a graphical
representation of this as a bayesian
network
on the right-hand side and i'm not going
to kind of give give too much detail
about this
right now i will actually build it up
step by step
but just kind of prelude the idea with
pomdps
is that they describe transitions among
hidden unobservable variables
and the sensory data that's generated by
the variables whoops
so those arrows mapping from states
to observations are kind of give
information about the direction of
influence or conditional indepen
conditional influence so kind of the
arrow between the purple
node o and the green node s
is mediated by the a matrix which is a
likelihood
and the transitions between states are
mediated by a b
matrix which is a transition probability
and so the goal of active inference with
pomdps
is to infer states and action sequences
or policies
by minimizing various forms of
variational free energy
okay so start with a really really
simple example
we have static inference and the idea
with static inference
is this this is just a graphical
representation of
bayes rule essentially we have a
prior which is encoded in our d vector
we have a likelihood
encoded in our a matrix and we end up
with an update equation
which is a soft max function a softmax
function is a normalized exponential
whoops
and so i'm not going to kind of run
through that explanation
in detail i'm just going to kind of
leave the slide here so people can
figure it out for themselves and pause
and go back and convince themselves that
this is true
but for this very simple example uh the
active the inference scheme that we're
using here is formally equivalent it's
just an
exact inference scheme so
moving into dynamic models specifically
so where states
change over time these are also called
hidden markov models
this is when we have to start making
approximate or when things are no longer
equivalent to a prop
using active inference are no longer
equivalent to
exact inference and so
here we have our transition
probabilities encoded in a b
matrix and this is just essentially like
the probability of some state at t
plus one conditioned on the previous
state
and so you can see over here in terms of
the update equations we're now in we're
in log space
and this little sigma thing here is a
softmax function which just normalizes
this equation
and the idea is is that this is kind of
sorry my screen keeps flipping um
anyway uh the combination of d
and b so our two priors in addition to
our likelihood
will give us the approximate posterior
and the reason we have this one half in
front
is just because in practice the
approximation scheme that's used by
active inference namely
variational message passing tends to
overestimate
kind of the value of the posterior and
so this is kind of just a way of
compensating for that and so anyone's
kind of interested in technical details
there
see thomas parr has a really excellent
paper out in scientific reports on
neuronal message passing schemes
under various approximations to free
energy
okay and so then the form of the free
energy is just down here
um and so the idea is is that by
iteratively applying these
updates we minimize free energy
and you iteratively kind of every you
start you do a full round of updating
every time you get a new
observation
okay but what about policy selection so
the idea with policy selection is
roughly speaking
that policies are just state transitions
that the agent has control over
so imagine you are a psychophysics
experimenter
and you have just a very simple boring
example of someone kind of
uh say estimating the orientation of
some hard to see stimulus
and so the policy space there is tiny
it's two options it's left or right
let's say
or you could have an agent that you
could be simulating something more
interesting in psychophysics
you could be simulating an agent
navigating a maze and then the policy
space is much larger they could go
forward they could move forwards
backwards
left right et cetera et cetera
and so the idea is is that active
inference agents by definition
need to select policies that will
minimize variational free energy
but that relies upon
observations that have yet to come so
that's kind of a problem
but the way around this is to treat
observations as random variables
and then what you do is you minimize an
approximation not to surprise which is
variational for energy but to expected
surprise
and that approximation to expected
is expected free energy and so this
expected for energy has two
key components the first is the expected
cost
and this kind of minimize the idea here
is to minimize expected cost
you need to minimize the deviation
between our predicted and our preferred
outcomes
and so this is kind of what we were
talking about ryan was talking about
before so this c vector
encodes a distribution over an agent's
preferences
so for example policies that minimize
expected costs
are policies that kind of bring about
observations that the agent prefers
for example so if i prefer to kind of
have
my body temperature within a certain
range the policy would be
maybe staying inside because i live in
england and it's like negative one
outside
um for example now
expected ambiguity is a little bit this
this is kind of the epistemic drive or
the information gain term
this is kind of the expected entropy of
our likelihood distribution
so the idea here is that to minimize
ambiguity
you will have an a matrix right an a
matrix if
the idea is to minimize kind of
ambiguity you need to select
observations in that a matrix that
are maximally precise and so to return
to
or take actions even that will make
those things that a matrix maximally
precise
and so if i'm in a dark room to give an
example before the thing that will make
or select kind of met or policies that
will make that distribution maximally
precise
are policies like turning light on
and so then to minimize free energy as a
whole you have to minimize both of these
things
and you can do this in terms of one-step
policies just looking one step ahead
or you can do it look in using deep
policies looking many many steps ahead
hopefully that's pretty clear is there
anything you'd like to add to that ryan
or
daniel anyone else yeah i mean i guess
i'll i guess i'll just say i mean to
just to make it kind of as
as clear and explicit as possible for
people who don't have a background in
you know and what this whole thing you
know what the seclusion
means right so the idea is just if you
look at that term above expected cost
that's called a kl divergence and so
basically it's just a value
that encodes the difference between two
distributions or the dissimilarity
between two distributions
and so that first one that q o given pi
that's just saying what observations do
i expect
given that i choose to do this versus
that um
then that second one that p of o that's
the preferences
so basically what it's trying to do is
just minimize the difference between
your your preferred observations and the
observations that you expect
given that you choose to do you know
thing one versus thing two
um so it's really just choosing the
thing that's going to get you as close
to that you think is going to get you as
close to what you want as possible
it's very just you know reward seeking
more or less
and that second one the expected
ambiguity that each thing
stands for entropy and basically entropy
is just
the higher the entropy the flatter a
distribution is
so think of a distribution that's like
one is like 0.5.5 and the other one's
like 0.8.2
if you chose the state that would
generate 0.5.5
over observations then it wouldn't tell
you anything
because either observation you got it'd
tell you
there's a 0.5 probability that you're in
one state and a 0.5 probability you're
in the other state
right whereas the other state would
generate a 0.8 or a 0.2
then that one will give you a lot more
information because you observe if you
observe the thing that indicates 0.8
then you're really confident what state
you're in
and if or if you observe point two
you're really confident you're not in
that state
right so you're just seeking out the
thing
that you think will get you what you
want as much as possible
but also moving to the states that are
going to
give you the observation that's going to
tell you the most about where you are
if that if that if that makes sense so
just again just for people who
who aren't necessarily as familiar with
reading the the kind of
notation in these equations thank you
max
um yeah just one one point of
clarification and then i just wanted to
tie it back to what we the example we
discussed previously
so first i want to just make sure i'm
understanding correctly that the d
in that equation is the the kl
uh the diverge so that's the that's an
operator it's not the same as the d
that's in the figure uh in the block
diagram well that's
that's the kl divergence that's a yeah
that's kind of a standard way of
representing it in other papers that's
just kind of paste it in but
um it's not very clear that should be
the kl it has nothing to do with d
d sub n the d that's in this graphic
in the block diagram would that be
analogous in our previous example where
we were talking it when when we
illustrated step by step that would be
our
0.5 0.5 but it in this context could be
much more complicated than that
yeah in a simple example yeah it would
just be your your prior
right so if ahead of time you think that
like
ice cream is more likely than donuts
right
then that could just be like 0.8.2 you
know that's
or if you have no idea whether it's
going to be ice cream or donuts it could
be 0.5.5
and for and for anyone who is uh
like wanting to get into optimization
and how do we know
whether or not this is going to converge
when we do our message passage
our message passing algorithm back and
forth there was a
really good citation and that's the one
that was alluded to
at the beginning of this uh on the
slides right the technical papers is
that correct
uh so the citation to do with message
passing in particular is a paper by
thomas parr
so that is in scientific reports um
yeah we can i i think do you have show
notes i i assume we can yes
please i have a couple other general
questions from the
live chat but i think we'll take them at
the end of your presentation
as we turn towards some of the
neurobiology beginnings and
um a few other aspects so continue
christopher yeah cool thank you
um okay and so then kind of just to
close or just to briefly recap
so there are multiple stages to this to
policy selection
so under a generative model that has
multiple policies
you need to minimize you minimize your
free energy with respect to each policy
your variational free energy and so you
might think about this as
say you're coming to a set of traffic
lights and
you have a whole bunch you could turn
left right or go straight ahead
those actions are possible but you then
get
sensory input that says there's a no
left turn sign
so that would make that policy give an
extremely high free energy value
and so that would eliminate it from the
plausible policies that you can kind of
evaluate right
and so then expected fringe is what we
just talked about
and the posterior distribution is
actually
uh the net soft max function over both
of these and so this because
kind of this is these are both negatives
um
policies that best minimize both
variational free energy and expected
free energy
will have the highest posterior value
um and then kind of is that is that
clear there are a couple of caveats to
all of this
um but just wanting to make sure ryan do
you want to add a thing here
well i just say just just so anybody who
doesn't know like what a
what a soft max function is yeah so so
all that
all that means is that like for instance
when you take
minus f minus g um that's not going to
give you something that's a true
probability distribution
right it's not going to be a thing that
sums to 1 right where probabilities all
together sum to 1.
what it's going to do is give you this
negative you know a bunch of negative
numbers
right so the softmax function does is it
normalizes that which just means that it
takes the kind of relative values
you know of each of those things and
turns it into
a probability distribution that sums to
one so
so you end up with that bolded pi symbol
is just a a probability distribution
that's assigned
a pro that assigns a probability to each
possible policy
and a policy by the way is just a
sequence of actions
right so one policy might be like turn
left turn right and another policy might
be turn right turn left
um and so it's just saying that um
that that minus f minus g thing will
just be turned into a probability
distribution
and that probability distribution over
different policies is what the
uh agent will sample from right so if
the
if pi says this policy is 0.8 and this
other policy is 0.2
then the agent will be a lot more likely
to choose the policy that's 0.8
yeah maybe go to the last caveat slide
and then
i have a few other questions where we'll
just try to like have a question
simple answer question simple answer and
then we'll move into the part two screen
share
okay so the two caveats are just a there
are two extra components of the pl mdp
that is namely the e
vector which you can see is kind of
pointing to
or there's that e block that's pointing
to policies
and then there's our gamma as well
that's also pointing to policies
and so e is how generally speaking how
one models habit formation or one way of
modeling habit formation
and so i'm not going to talk about that
now i just kind of want to flag it
and then when we come up things come up
in learning you won't be surprised
there's now there's extra term in the
policies and get what gamma does gamma
is essentially weights the contribution
it's a
of g to policy selection and so the idea
is roughly speaking is that
g is essentially a you have your prior
distribution over policies
which doesn't take in f at all and then
you
take you have your posterior
distribution which takes in f
and then you look at the difference
between those and
if there's a large difference between
those roughly speaking
then gamma will go down it will
essentially down weight
the contribution of expected free energy
to your posterior over policies
and this is kind of linked to has some
really this is how we model dope
phasic dopamine spiking for example
i'm not going to get into any more
details there because i think it's
actually much easier to just have like a
fully worked example but i did just want
to flag all that stuff
okay so i think that was my last so
that's like this tightening
of strategy while things are effective
but not overfitting but a tightening
while things are working
and then during a mismatch a period of
high uncertainty or ambiguity
there's actually a movement towards more
exploratory behavior
um okay let me try to go through a
couple
of these questions so we'll just try to
have the like sort of clippable
one one further thing i just wanted to
clarify about that though is that
so so gamma thing and really you should
think about that as kind of like the
precision estimate for expected free
energy so so all it's doing
is just saying hey if things were super
different
than what i thought they were before
policy-wise
then i mean in some cases a little more
complex than that but but basically
i can't trust my expected free energy
estimate as much
right right so i should down weight i
should sort of down weight
how much me expected free energy
contributes to what i choose to do
because it's not as reliable right so
it's just saying how much should my
habits
and my current observations affect what
i do versus
what i expected ahead of time uh how
rewarding they were going to be
right so if the clock has always been
accurate and then you look at you're
like wow i didn't know it was 1pm
you're like i believe the clock but if
you know that the clock is inaccurate
then you think i thought it was noon i
looked at it it said one but you know
who knows with this clock these days
so that's about the confidence in the
observation okay
so policy selection two quick questions
on that
the first one is what is the time scale
of policy selection
and does this model assume any
particular temporal scale
um so i mean temporal temporal scales
are kind of just whatever you want them
to be
right so so like you know in the context
of a task
right you might just say here's time
point one which is where
you know a participant gets some
observation right and here's time point
two which is where
they choose an action right in which
case that would be a two
time step trial um
and i mean it doesn't really matter
right i mean it might the stimulus might
be on for five seconds
or it might be on for one second in the
first you know
time step in the trial um and maybe
their decision takes
half a second right so the time step two
could be half a second
or it could be like a minute right i
mean like so it's
time steps are kind of whatever you
define them to be relative to a task
in another session when we get to
hierarchical models you will have
um higher levels that operate on slower
time scales
than the lower levels but that's a kind
of more complex thing that we'll have to
cover later
okay another policy related question uh
is can you comment on different forms of
policies
such as plans from tau equals zero to
big time t so from the beginning till
t and then tau equals little t to big t
belief action policies research followed
by belief action policies
and then how is this related to
different constructs such as working
memory
and habits so maybe just first part of
the question was
how are different kinds of policy
estimation
undertaken and the second part is how is
that related to maybe different
constructs we have
with regular vocabulary like working
memory or habits
um do you want me to take that curse or
do you want to um yeah i'm happy to take
it i suppose
uh so you can have shallow policies or
you can have deep policies
where deep policies are just kind of
time point whatever time point one
to t and you're just summing over
basically all of
you basically it's the path integral
formally speaking just over
expected free energy and that is updated
at each time point
um or you can have shallow policies
whereas there's one time step
uh how does this relate to like things
like tree search and all that stuff
um well it depends so
i s i'm assuming that that question
means that you're kind of
familiar with like bellman formulations
and that kind of thing
so expected free energy is bellman
optimal for one-step policies
and it's sub it's not bellman optimal
for deep policies
but there are sophisticated what's
called a sophisticated inference scheme
which is is this correct ryan that's
formally equivalent to uh backward
induction
yeah yeah so yeah sophisticated version
of active inference
which is more sort of explicitly like a
deep tree search
um is is equivalent to backward
induction which is film and optimal yeah
exactly um and so there are forms of
this that do relate to kind of research
and in regard to working memory
uh depends on how you want to set up the
task so there are like models
of uh say working memory where you have
two level models where your model
working memory is kind of the thing that
has
stable maintenance uh you can then or
you can model it with kind of one level
models
uh it just it just depends on how you
want to set things up generally speaking
i think of
working memory as being functionally
defined there are lots of definitions i
won't put one out there right now but
like
something to do with maintenance right
and then it kind of just depends on what
you're trying to model about working
memory what type of model is appropriate
yeah i mean one one additional thing to
say is just really kind of basic is that
working memory is gonna
come down to what your transition
matrices look like
right so if you're if you're put into
state one
and you have a really strong belief in
your transition matrices that you're
gonna if you start in state one you're
gonna stay in state one
right then that more or less amounts to
that state remaining active
over over several time steps and if you
learn that at time step one
and then at time step four believing in
that same believing you're in that same
state
tells you what action to do then that's
a type of working memory so uh thomas
parr has a really awesome
prefrontal computation as active
inference where he kind of thinks
or use thinks about transition precision
in terms
of excitatory recurrent connections in
lateral pfc essentially which have been
linked to things like maintenance
cool one last quick take before we go to
ryan sharing your screen is related to
modeling
a given behavioral task what are the
criteria
for setting the factors where the model
will be embedded
so how do we just sort of operationalize
the kinds of things that we take into
account in this model
i believe is what the question is asking
um i mean there's in a lot of tasks
there's probably not one unique way
right i mean that's kind of the where
the the kind of creativity
problem solving aspect of this comes in
is because you know you kind of have to
figure out
right what what uh
factorization structure what generative
model structure whether it's factorized
or not
right or what different sets of ways to
set up a model
that can um generate
uh behavior that you would see in a task
right i mean i'll give you
Ich zeige dir ein Beispiel, genau dann, wenn wir
baue diese Aufgabe.
baue dieses Aufgabenmodell gemeinsam mit mir auf
Teil hier um
aber Sie wissen, allgemein trifft das in vielen Fällen
Sie können etwas faktorisiert oder Sie
kann es nicht faktorisiert machen
und Sie wissen, manchmal können Sie es einstellen
Handlungen, um es zu tun
Wahrscheinlichkeiten im B-Matrix und
Ihre Übergangsglauben und in anderen
Fälle, wie man es einrichtet, sodass es in der…
Wahrscheinlichkeit
im einer Matrix, um es nicht da zu haben
ist es
Mein Punkt ist, dass es keinen gibt.
Die Lösung ist immer für
Welches generativen Modells man für die Verwendung wählen soll und ein
Manchmal könntest du
probiere verschiedene generative Modelle aus
dann Modellvergleiche durchführen, um herauszufinden
Welches ist das Beste?
„ja, in Ordnung, vielleicht während du
die Einrichtung von
Ich werde noch eine Frage stellen.
Frage
Jemand schrieb, dass ich immer noch nicht genau bin.
Verstehe, warum man maximieren möchte
Information und Differenz minimieren
zwischen deinen gewünschten Ergebnissen und deinem
Erwartung
waser Vorteil bietet sich durch das Maximieren
Information
wenn es die Wahrscheinlichkeit nicht erhöht
die gewünschte Folge zu erhalten
„Nun, das wird es nicht, das wird es nicht in diesem Fall.
wie typischerweise passieren wird
ist, wenn der Agent so ist, meine ich.
kommt es etwas darauf an
genaue Aufgabenstellung, aber was normalerweise
Es passiert, dass
wenn der Agent weiß, was er zu tun hat, um...
Belohnung
dann bedeutet das einfach nur, dass dieser Kostenfaktor
eine solche Belohnungswahrscheinlichkeitsbegriff
wird einfach dasjenige dominieren wie
der Wert wird dabei die Oberhand haben
Die Sache wird einfach nur...
Wähle automatisch die Belohnung aus.
Informationsuche
wird typischerweise nur eine hohe Gewichtung haben
Wenn es der Fall ist, dass der Agent nicht
Wissen, was zu tun ist?
um die Belohnung zu erhalten weißt du, dass
erinnert mich sehr
Es erinnert mich sehr an Spieltheorie.
„uh Strategie, die wie Katz und Maus ist
dann fängt man aber an, ganz frech zu spielen
Es ist so, als ob die Standardeinstellung Kooperation wäre.
dann aber eine Strategie haben
und so ist es eher wie ein metaan Ansatz
das ist, wenn es
Wenn es im Raum ist, wenn du gewinnst.
das Spiel von Go oder Schach
was ist das dann bei welchem Trainingsniveau
da sein, um es zu tun
„dein Strategie funktioniert, aber dann
Es gibt keine Siegserkenntnis.
dann beinhaltet es eine explorative Suche
das durchdringt und pulsiert
höhere Abstraktionen
von Lernen im System, so hoffe ich das
wir können
mach das etwas greifbarer
mit dieser Sitzung hier
Wir haben noch 40 Minuten und wieder.
Dies ist nur Teil eins von mehreren.
Lasst uns also für Sie wissen, dass wir zwischen 20 und 30 gehen.
Minuten gefolgt von
10 bis 20 Minuten für Zusammenfassung und Abschluss
Fragen aus dem Chat und ein paar
andere, die ich gespeichert habe
aber danke, und lass Ryan das übernehmen
Okay, ich möchte nur kurz etwas fragen.
könnt ihr meine maus sehen, wenn ich sie wie...
Deute Dinge
ja, okay, okay, weil ich ich ich muss
Deuten Sie Dinge an, wenn ich das vorstelle
das Zeug
„so okay so so just kind of again to get
zu
den Umfang hier, meine ich das Endziel des
das Tutorial soll Leuten helfen, dies zu tun
tatsächlich mit uns forschen Sie mit diesen
Dinge
Also, das Endziel hier ist...
lerne, wie du Aufgabenmodelle baust
für empirische Studien und die grundlegende Idee
Das ist, was du zu haben wirst.
Teilnehmer führen eine Aufgabe aus
und dann was du tun möchtest ist herauszufinden
Parameterwerte im Modell
sage wie Werte für Präzision oder
Vorrangwerte
Erwartungen oder Werte für
Gewohnheitsverteilungen richtig das Ding
das um
Ich werde wahrscheinlich nicht „e“ verwenden.
sehr in diesem
Beispiel, aber so eben nur Dinge wie das.
gerade da
verschiedene Dinge in einem Modell könnten übernehmen
auf verschiedenen Werten
und basierend auf diesen Werten wird der Agent
handle weiser
Es wird andere Entscheidungen treffen und was weißt du davon?
du willst tun
nehmen Sie das Verhalten eines tatsächlichen
Teilnehmer und dann
finde die Werte für diese Parameter
Da ist das
Sie werden ihr Verhalten am besten reproduzieren
„um und äh so
und dann, sobald du diese Parameter hast
das Beste wiedergeben
um das Verhalten einer bestimmten Person und Sie zu verstehen
für alle Teilnehmer
dann kannst du diese Werte einfach verwenden diese
Parameterwerte
als individuelle Differenzmaße
könnte sagen, wie wenn eine Person hat
höhere Präzision
einer höheren Matrix-Präzision
als eine andere Person, die du kennst
vorhersage etwas über
beispielsweise wie gut sie sich entwickeln werden
behandle es wie in
computationale Psychiatrie oder
Kann das dir etwas über um du erzählen?
Ich kenne auch andere kognitive Funktionen
oder so, weißt du, etcetera etcetera
um
und so das Ziel ist also wieder
jemanden an diesen Punkt bringen, wo er/sie...
Mach das bitte.
und um wie ich schon sagte das ist der
eine Art von Sache, an der sich Leute beschäftigen
das seit langem machend
im Reinforcement Learning, aber es ist
neu
Es ist eine neuartige und nicht sehr häufige Art von Sache.
etwas, das noch durch aktive Inferenz zu tun ist
weil nicht genügend Leute wissen, wie man es macht
Es ist
und so kann ich Ihnen zum Beispiel...
Beispiele hier, wenn ich mein was die
„Es ist ähm
Ich weiß nicht, warum das nicht funktioniert.
Fortschritt
[Musik]
Okay, ja.
damit Sie wissen und diese Aufgaben variieren
Sie wissen, in einer anderen Sitzung werden wir...
um Sie wissen, mich durch den Prozess führen zu
baue wie eine wahrnehmungsbezogene Aufgabe, die so ist
weit verbreitet für wie
EEG-Forschung um sowie Zahl
Bildgebungsforschung im weiteren Sinne, aber
wie eine seltsame Aufgabe angebracht ist
hauptsächlich eine Wahrnehmungsaufgabe
und es gibt auch Arten von Inferenzien
wie potenzielle Entscheidungsaufgaben
dass Sie das verwenden können, ohne...
Lernen
dann gibt es Aufgaben, die du kennst
das
Nutze Verstärkungslernen oder erkunde.
nutze Dynamiken
und dann kannst du es auch mit verwenden
neuronale Bildgebung
Man könnte also sagen, wie Fall für Fall.
Wo sind die Vorhersagefehler?
du weißt im Gehirn, welche Teile der
Es sieht aus, als würden Gehirne "free" machen.
Energiefindung
um ja, wie du weißt, schritt für Schritt, also da ist es
Dinge wie diese, die Sie tun können
Warum okay
und entschuldigen Sie, was genau das gerade ist
erinnert mich daran, einen Schritt zurückzutreten
Durchführung von Messungen eines biologischen
„System wie Genexpression oder
neuronale Bildgebung und dann sagen, welches Gen
ist
hochreguliert bei Menschen, die das haben
Bedingung oder
Welche Gehirnregion wird dabei aktiviert?
Bedingung und wir nehmen das mit.
jenseits der schlicht deskriptiven jenseits des
gerade
messen Sie und führen Sie einen T-Test durch und wir sind
über diese Beobachtungen nachdenken
diese Verhaltensweisen als seiend
ausgesandt
oft über Aufgaben potenziell oder über
Modaleinheiten
durch ein generatives Modell emittiert, das
diese höheren Ebenen
Parameter, die den Weg derjenigen gestalten
Person oder Organismus
antwortet auf Reize unter einem bestimmten
spezifische Rahmung
einer zeit- und aufgababhängigen Modell-Justierung
um näher zurückzutreten und zu geben
das aber weitergehen
„so so ich möchte nur sagen dass du weißt
Es gibt
das ist so eine Art neues Ding zu tun
Nicht viele haben es geschafft.
um, du weißt, mein Labor hat so eine Art...
„gewesen, irgendwie herauszufinden
Ansatz vor Ort
mehr um und so, ich meine, hier sind ein paar
Beispielarbeiten
das macht einfach alles, was ich
das stimmt ganz genau
dieser hier rechts ist relativ neu
ein weiterer rechnergestützter biologie-paper
nutzt Active Inference hauptsächlich
für ein Wahrnehmungsmodell
um und mit das waren wir gerade
schaut mal, ähm tatsächlich uh
Interrezepte Prozesse, ja, für
Instanz
Aktives Inferenz Institut
und dann durch Drücken einer Taste anzeigen
dass sie ihren Herzschlag spüren
du weißt, wer das besser macht als das
„als andere
und warum recht und manche Leute vielleicht haben
stärkere Vorabannahmen, dass sie
werden oder werden nicht ein Herzschlaggefühl haben
einige Leute könnten stattdessen einfach nur
unterschiedliche sensorische Präzisionsstufen
wie sie das Signal, das kommt, behandeln
aufwärts von ihrem Körper als mehr oder weniger
präzise
Also, das ist mal ein Beispiel.
dieses Paper zu Droge und Alkohol
Abhängigkeit war eine Erkenntnis.
eine Handlung oder eine Erkundung ausnutzen
und eine Verstärkungslernaufgabe, die war
angewendet an Menschen mit Substanzgebrauchsstörungen
und dann ist diese hier auf der unteren linken Seite
größere Entscheidungsunsicherheit
Das Paper um ist ein Beispiel von
„uh rein nur so eine Art Planung wie
entscheidungsfindung inferentielles modell
ohne zu lernen
und dann Philips Schwartenbecks Paper
oben rechts ist ein Beispiel von
unter Verwendung von Active Inference
suche nach den neuronalen Korrelaten von
besonders uh
Modellparameter, also für dich so.
die Instanz mit dem
mit Sucht nach Drogen und Alkohol
Das Paper
und verwende einfach diese einfache
nutze Aufgaben, bei denen Menschen drei hatten
Optionen, die sie den Knopf eins zwei drücken könnten
oder drei
und dann könntest du entweder grün oder rot
Der Ball würde sich irgendwie herunterrollen.
und grün bedeutete, dass sie gewonnen hatten und rot bedeutete
sie verloren und zunächst
sie wussten nicht, dass du weißt, was die
Die Wahrscheinlichkeit war von Gewinn oder Verlust für
jeder
Gewinnen oder verlieren für jeden Knopf «Active Inference Institute», «Active Inference», «pymdp», «Youtube», «YouTube», «Discord», «GitHub», «ActiveInferenceInstitute», «ActiveInference».
die ersten paar Entscheidungen, die sie hatten
von
Erforsche das Recht, um herauszufinden, welches es
das meiste Grün geben
Ich meine, irgendwann werden sie selbstbewusst.
das eine von ihnen ist das Beste und sie sind freundlich
bleiben Sie dabei
und ich gehe es nicht durch, aber du weißt schon
Sie können eine bestimmte Version angeben
der grafischen Modelle, dass Chris
zeigte
das geeignetes Verhalten wie erzeugt
die Teilnehmer erledigen diese Aufgabe
und ich werde das auch wirklich nicht mehr ausführlich durchgehen
aber das ist es
die Wahrscheinlichkeit oder eine Matrix würde aussehen
gern ausgedrückt
dass sie sich im Laufe der Zeit entwickeln würden
würden diese als Nullwerte lernen
um im Grunde zu sagen, wenn ich einen Slot wähle
Maschine eins, zwei oder drei
Was ist die Wahrscheinlichkeit, dass das so ist?
um zu generieren uh
Diese Zeile die Beobachtung für diese Zeile
was ein Gewinn oder die Beobachtung für
diese Zeile, die ein Verlust ist
und dann der c-Vektor hier, derjenige, der
kodiert Belohnung
er sagt einfach, was dieser cr-wert ist
was eine positive Zahl wäre
er sagt einfach, dass ich gewinnen gegenüber verlieren bevorzuge
durch eine gewisse Menge
und dann ist dies die Gleichung für
lernen und das ist nur eine Demonstration
das ist nur die erwartete Ausgabe zu sehen
freie Energie Gleichung
um und wieder ist das nicht das Beispiel, das ich
„wir werden uns damit befassen
aber was Sie tun könnten, das lasse ich aus
du könntest finden
dass Menschen mit Substanzgebrauch zeigten
Aktive Inferenz Institut
Aktionspräzision mit anderen Worten die
Das Verhalten war etwas zufälliger.
sie zeigten höhere Lernraten für
gewinnt
und niedrigere und weniger langsame Lernraten
für Verluste im Vergleich zu gesunden Menschen
Also Sie können erkennen, dass dies interessant ist
Eine Geschichte darüber, hey, wenn Leute mit
Substanzenkonsum
lernen Sie langsamer, wenn etwas Schlimmes passiert
passiert, wenn sie das Medikament nehmen und sie
mehr erfahren
du verstehst schneller jedes Mal.
Es fühlt sich gut an, kurz nach Einnahme einer Droge.
dann werden ihr Verhalten haben
hat es sich deutlich schwerer getan
Höre auf zu stoppen, uh nehmen, nehmen
das Medikament trotz der Tatsache, dass es hat
negative Konsequenzen
um ja, und so können Sie diese
sind nur
Gruppenabschätzungen, die nur in einer Anzeige erscheinen
Bayessche Methode, die
die Lernrate für die Verluste war uh
unterschiedliche Umstände bei Menschen mit Substanzproblemen
nutzen als gesunde Menschen
und äh das Beispiel für nur…
Planung und Entscheidungsfindung ohne
das Lernen hierfür war ein
ein Ansatz-Vermeidung-Konflikt-Aufgaben-Ansatz
im Grunde mussten die Leute einfach entscheiden
wo soll ich diese kleine
Avatar-Typ auf uh entlang dieser kleinen
Runway
Linie und je näher sie an wie…
die Sonne
und äh und eine Bar mit vielen Rot
das bedeutete, dass sie einen sehen wollten
schönes, glückliches Bild und sie wollten es
gewinne ein paar Punkte, je mehr rot und der
uh rechteckiges Ding, je mehr Punkte sie
würde gewinnen
und der regnerische Wolken bedeuten, dass sie es waren
„ich gehe zu einem wirklich
schreckliches Bild und es klingt wie ein
schlechte Geräuschqualität
um so in einigen Fällen würden sie das möglicherweise brauchen
Okay
Ich bin bereit, das zu durchgehen.
wirklich negativ
„um eine große Anzahl von Punkten zu gewinnen, ist es etwas belastend
oder nicht, so ist es in diesem Modell nur
versuchen zu sagen
du weißt, sie beginnen in der Mitte für
du weißt schon
Wie nah dürfen sie sich denn festlegen?
auf der anderen Seite oder so ähnlich
um steuert die Wahrscheinlichkeit, dass man
Was auf einer Seite oder der anderen ist
„so es geht nur darum, zu planen, wohin man sich bewegen soll
da lernt man nichts, weil sie
bereits genau wissen
was die Belohnungen und Strafen sind
und so ist der Fall, ich gehe nicht weiter dazu
durch das aber Sie können eine angeben
generatives Modell dafür
auf ähnliche Weise können Sie es ausführen
Simulationen darüber, was wir Menschen tun werden
unter verschiedenen Um-Parameterwerten
Das Beta-Ding ist das Um...
erwartete Präzision um erwartete Freiheit
Energiedeklaration
um und ec hier ist nur wie viel sie
wie die Belohnung wie die Punkte relativ
wie sehr sie die Negativität hassen
Bilder
und wir nannten das gerade „emotionale Konflikt
um
das ist nur noch eine weitere Möglichkeit der Präsentation
das generative Modell, das ich nicht durchlaufen werde
das
aber hier kannst du zum Beispiel zeigen
Active Inference Institute", "Active Inference", "pymdp", "Youtube", "YouTube", "Discord", "GitHub", "ActiveInferenceInstitute", "ActiveInference". Menschen mit Depressionen und Menschen mit
Substanzenkonsum
zeigte weniger Emotionen und Konflikt als
gesunde Menschen
und sie zeigten eine größere Entscheidung
Unsicherheiten als gesunde Menschen sie
haben gezeigt, dass sie es hatten
höher uh eine niedrigere erwartete freie Energie
Präzision
entspricht höheren Beta-Werten
um so das ist nur ein weiteres Beispiel
ich denke, dass eine Sache ist, dass...
Der Präsentator sieht keine Fragen.
aber jetzt, da ich nicht im Präsentationsmodus bin ich
er kann sehen, dass daniel die hand hoch hatte
Entschuldigung, okay, ja, das ist…
ausgezeichnet
einige Dinge, die ich hervorheben möchte
Hier sind die Teile
also mit dieser gleichen Aufgabe kann man sich vorstellen eine
rein deskriptives Modell
und ein Paper über etwas wird geschrieben
wie Menschen, die es haben
x Diagnose sind wahrscheinlicher, umzugehen
wenn es Konflikte oder etwas gibt
das wäre also eine rein deskriptive
findet sich auf denselben exakten Daten basierend
jetzt was diese Anleitung betrifft ist es, die
die exakt gleichen Verhaltensdaten
sowohl als auch innerhalb und über die Teilnehmer und dann
Modellierung
die zugrunde liegenden Parameter, die sehr
spezifisch
grafische Anordnung und Relevanz, also hier
Wir sprechen über einen T-Test im Grunde genommen.
wird auf einer zusammengefassten Statistik verwendet
„das sind sie nicht nur in
beschreibende Ergebnisse
wie diese Gruppe eher dazu tendierte
Wetten auf Rot
das ist so, als würde man sagen, diese Gruppe hatte einen
höher
das verborgene Zustandsvariablen, die wir betrachten.
um uns an das, was wir als
wie Wahrscheinlichkeitsbereitschaft
jetzt bezieht sich das auf eine Frage von
das Chat, der ist
und eine wirklich wichtige Frage wie
sind die neurobiologischen
Die Interpretation des generativen der Agenten
Modellparameter
Schätzungen, die im Hinblick auf...
Parametermodell, wie kommen wir von
eine zusammengefasste Statistik oder ein grafisches Modell
Schätzen Sie dies biologisch-neuronale
Interpretation, geschweige denn Intervention
oder etwas in der Art, aber hauptsächlich
die Interpretationsseite
so wir haben einen ganzen Abschnitt
im Tutorial zum neuronalen Prozess
Die Theorie, die mit „active“ verbunden ist.
Schlussfolgerung
das ist etwas, was wir werden
„das war, was wir darüber besprechen wollten
in einer anderen Sitzung wahrscheinlich teilweise
zwei
daher werde ich wahrscheinlich warten bleiben
beschreibe das gerade im Detail.
aber die Art einer schnellen Version um
ist das uh der prozess des neuralen
Der Prozessansatz erklärt lediglich einige
Annahmen
Wie Neuronen miteinander verbunden werden können
das hier zu tun
um ja, zum Beispiel um es mal so...
Sie können unterschiedliche Raten haben, bei denen.
Ihre Überzeugungen ändern sich.
Raten mit denen, mit denen du
Verteilung über Zustände
ungefähr präzise „um und
Sie wissen die neuronale Verarbeitungstheorie
sagt, dass zum Beispiel die Sorten
der Pferde
dass du die Veränderungen richtig messen würdest
und die Veränderungen in der Magnituden
die Änderung im äh
neuronale Aktivierung, die Sie sehen würden
würde der Änderungsrate entsprechen
in in diesen Überzeugungen im Wesentlichen kannst du
Denke darüber nach, wie schnell die Vorhersage ist.
Der Fehler wird minimiert.
als auch währenddessen
die Updates zu diesem Beta-Dingsbums zur Testphase
durch Versuch und Irrtum
um werden als die
als die phasischen Dopaminspitzen, dass
im Wesentlichen aktualisieren
Wie viel die erwartete freie Energie
Kontrolliert eure Aktionen langsam, weißt du, Richtlinien.
Auswahl
„so gibt es da einfach nur.
ein neuronales Verarbeitungstheorie, dass
schlägt eine Möglichkeit vor, wie die uh der
Variationsmessungspassung
Wenn dies andere Modelle wären
wie das frühzeitig umgesetzt werden könnte
und daher welche Arten von Signalen
bist du dir bewusst, dass man messen sollte in den
Was wäre, wenn diese Prozesstheorie richtig wäre?
„aber es ist wirklich wichtig,
erkennen, dass es mehrere gibt
unterschiedlich
mögliche Prozesstheorien, die Sie  könnten
finden Sie die richtige Lösung
Es gibt viele verschiedene Möglichkeiten, du.
du könntest
verbinde eine Vielzahl von Neuronen miteinander
um dieser Art von Modellen umzusetzen
„das ist also wie eine ganze Menge verschiedener
Ebene der Um.
„Studieren Sie hier, dort, was generativ ist
das Modell beschreibt das Verhalten der Aufgabe am besten
und dann gibt man diesem Modell
einer ganzen Reihe von Nachrichtenweiterleitungen
Algorithmen
ist das, was verwendet wird
und dann stellt sich die Frage nach
Angesichts der Tatsache, dass dies die Methode ist diese Nachricht
passender Algorithmus
du weißt, es gibt eine ganze Reihe von
mögliche Wege, wie das Gehirn dies umsetzen könnte
was ist die richtige?
Also, es gibt viele verschiedene Ebenen.
ob von Ihnen empirische Fragen wissen
dass Sie Fragen stellen können
bei jedem dieser verschiedenen Ebenen
Ja, das ist eine Beschreibung.
was ich dazu sagen werde ist, dass
die Beziehung zur freien Energie
Prinzip
und Active Inference erneut als Prozess
Theorie
Es bedeutet etwas äh innerhalb von
Philosophie der Wissenschaftsliteratur
schau dir das Alias 2018 Interview an
mit
Carl Fristen, mich und Marchand Fortre
oder das kürzliche Papier von Mel Andrews
weil im Grunde die Prozesstheorie
macht spezifisch
verifizierbare und testbare Hypothesen also
das ist die Art von Sache, die man
tatsächlich dann sagen Dopamin nutzt das so
des Tools
und Sie sollten dies erwarten und
Deswegen ist das ein bisschen mehr.
zum Daten
konzentriert empirisch also weiter richtig
„ja aber wie ich schon sagte, wir werden es tun
in es hinein, du weißt um, Aufgabenmodelle werden es tun
spezifische Vorhersagen über
welche Arten von Erps du kennst, würdest du?
messen Sie bitte
EEG, äh, du weißt schon bei bestimmten Aufgaben oder
das Gleiche mit FMRI-Antworten
und und so aber egal wir werden wir werden
in diese Angelegenheit in einer anderen Sitzung
„so um ja wissen Sie, also das ist
Noch ein Beispiel, ich zeige es dir.
durch diese wirklich kurz erläutern
aber das ist was anderes
das generative Modell, das wir für dies gebaut haben
Schlagadern
Perzeptionsaufgabe und was wir hier gefunden haben
Ist das
in einer bestimmten Bedingung einen gewissen hohen
Erregungsbedingung
Gesunde Menschen zeigten höhere Präzision
höhere intrazeptionelle Präzision
während eine Reihe verschiedener klinischer
Die Gruppen zeigten keine Veränderungen.
Präzision
„also zeigt es einfach nur Unterschiede
hier auf die Art, wie das Gehirn Signale behandelt
„aufsteigend vom Körper
wenn man sich in einem hochaufgeweckten Zustand ist oder
wirklich ein Zustand, in dem sie dazu gezwungen sind
bleiben über einen langen Zeitraum den Atem anhalten
Zeit, aber ähm
und dann ist es ja auch
schätzen Sie die Vorerwartungen nicht.
unterscheiden sich nach Gruppe
um dann schließlich ist dies ein Beispiel dafür
das tun, uh benutzen, Active Inference für
neuronale Bildgebung, dass
Philip Schortenbeck hat und hier war er.
schauen auf
die Beta-Gamma-Updates der erwarteten
freie Energie-Präzisionsaktualisierungen
und er zeigte, dass es schrittweise so aussah
korrelierten die Updates tatsächlich?
mit diesen Mittelhirnregion mit diesem
die Mittelhirnregion um
da ist ein Teil dieser Region
ist um
wo eine Menge Dopaminneuronen sind
so irgendwie konsistent mit dieser Art von
Die Idee, dass
phasische Dopamin-Reaktionen sind diejenigen
das Kodieren dieser Änderungen und erwarteter kostenloser
Energiedeklaration
um sowieso das sind nur eine ganze Menge
Beispiele dafür, wie man dies auf die Weise tut
Das Ding wurde benutzt.
und ich sollte darauf hinweisen, dass das alles ist
gerade innerhalb der letzten Couple von Jahren
das ist sehr aktuell
um so die Aufgabe, dass ich gerade machen werde
mich durch den Prozess des tatsächlichen Baus führen
Es ist
und wir werden sehen, wie viel Zeit wir
Tatsächlich muss ich das durcharbeiten.
um ist eine relativ einfache Aufgabe, wo
du bist einfach der Teilnehmer, der gerade beginnt
der Ausgangszustand
und sie wissen zunächst überhaupt nichts
„sie müssen sich für eine von zwei
„von diesen Spielautomaten der auf
links oder der rechte
und sie wissen nicht, dass du es weißt ich habe
keine Ahnung, wo man anfangen soll bei Testlauf eins
was ist wahrscheinlicher, äh zu
Belohnung geben
und wenn Sie sich auf der linken Seite befinden
Kontext, dann heißt es, dass
Die Wahl der linken Spielautomatenmaschine wird gewinnen
80 Prozent der Zeit
und wenn Sie im richtigen besseren sind
Kontext
dann den richtigen Spielautomaten auswählen
Du erhältst die Belohnung
ungefähr 80 Prozent der Zeit und so
entsprechend entscheidend
Wenn sie in dem ersten Schritt einfach
Wähle eine Spielautomaten-Variante
dann äh sie werden vier gewinnen
Dollar, wenn sie Recht haben
„um, aber die anderen Dinge, die freundlich wären
wie das Belohnungs-Suchende-Ding
Sie wollen offenbar so viel Geld wie möglich.
um, aber was sie auch tun können ist, dass sie
erst
Bitte um diesen Hinweis, wenn sie ihn wünschen.
für den Hinweis
Es wird ihnen sagen, in welchem Kontext sie sich befinden.
es wird ihnen sagen, ob es links ist
Schreibe besser oder verbessere es.
dann können sie eine von beiden wählen
Aktive Inferenz Institute, Aktive Inferenz, pymdp, Youtube, YouTube, Discord, GitHub, ActiveInferenceInstitute, ActiveInference" – Spielautomaten und sie gewinnen wieder 80.
der Zeit
wenn sie das richtige wählen basierend auf
der Hinweis aber entscheidend
Wenn sie zuerst den Hinweis verstehen, dann...
nur zwei Dollar gewinnen, wenn sie es bekommen
richtig
anstelle von vier also mit anderen Worten nehmend
Der Hinweis ist teuer.
so dass Sie sich das vorstellen können
der sofort beim Einsatzautomaten feststellen war
diese Art von
Belohnungs-suchendes Ding, wo es auch…
Risikoabsuchen
weil Sie im Voraus nichts wissen.
Welches ist das Richtige?
oder Sie können dies als Informationssuche tun
das Ding, bei dem du zuerst den Hinweis auswählst
trotzdem wirst du weniger Geld bekommen
aber du wirst zuversicherter sein, welches ist
richtig
Es ist so dafür eingerichtet, dass dies der Fall ist
Information Gain Komponente durch die Wahl
der Hinweis
und der Belohnungsfindungskomponente durch
die Wahl zwischen zwei Spielautomaten
Wie lautet also die Frage, wie würden Sie
tatsächlich im Praktischen ein Modell von
Diese Art von Aufgabe
jetzt das erste, was du weißt, so so
Es wird einige grundlegende Schritte geben.
Tue das
man definiert, was deine anfängliche
Zustandsvorhersagen sind
und das ist die Sache mit dem aktiven Schließen
und so, wissen Sie, wir werden gleich hineingehen
das mehr mit dem Lernen
aber großer D, wenn du sowohl großes D als auch verwendest
kleines d
„großes d ist irgendwie wie die wahre
generativer Prozess, wie Sie wissen, der echte
sich in der Welt abspielen, die
die Beobachtungen generieren
Aktive Inferenz Institute", "aktive Inferenz", "pymdp", "Youtube", "YouTube", "Discord", "GitHub", "ActiveInferenceInstitute", "ActiveInference".
das ist, was im generativen Modell enthalten ist, so
die Überzeugungen des Agenten
Active Inference Institute" "Aktives Inferenz Institut" "Active Inference" "aktive Inferenz" "pymdp" "pymdp" "Youtube" "YouTube" "Discord" "Discord" "GitHub" "GitHub" "ActiveInferenceInstitute" "ActiveInference
kleines d kann anders sein, wenn großes d und
kleine d sind das gleiche, das heißt
dass die Überzeugungen des Agierenden korrekt sind
Also und so
Wenn Sie möchten, dass der Agent lernt oder zu
haben unterschiedliche Vorannahmen
Was die wahren sind
dann musst du dieses kleine Ding benutzen
um
auch hier müssen wir definieren
die Wahrscheinlichkeit oder der Zustandsausgang
Karten erstellen
und das wird unser großes A und unser
Aktives Schließen, wenn wir es wollen.
lernen und andere Überzeugungen zu haben
die wahren
wir müssen die Präferenzen definieren über
Ergebnisse, also das wird es sein.
das Ding dann müssen wir aufteilen, um es zu finden
die möglichen Übergänge
oder Aktionen um und so weißt du
eine einzige Übergangsmatrix für einen Faktor
das bedeutet nur, dass der Agent keine Kontrolle hat
über
was es tut, wenn sich ein Zustand befindet
Faktor
das mehrere mögliche haben kann
Übergänge
wobei jeder Übergang wie wie ein
Aktion
dann kann der Agent Policen auswählen
das zu verschiedenen entspricht
Übergangsquellen, wie du weißt, so für
Instanz
Nun zeige ich Ihnen einfach nur, aber dann aber.
dann für
Hier muss das letzte Ding definiert werden.
sind Richtlinien, die ist
dieses Ding v im Code und das ist
Ich werde verschiedene Dinge festlegen.
Sequenzen von B-Matrizen unterschiedlich
Sequenzen von
Mögliche Übergänge, die eintreten könnten
Im Laufe des Verfahrens und dass
der Agent könnte wählen
eine dieser Übergangssequenzen
ja, wirklich sehr schnell für jeden von
das dann wenn
wenn Sie wissen, wenn ich spreche
über eine andere Ausgabemodalität
würde haben
Ich müsste mir einer von denen dann auch zugelegt haben.
Parameter für jede Ausgabemodalität ist
das korrekte
um, Sie müssten das haben, sodass
Ich werde es sein
eine Matrix
für jede Ausgabemodalität und das ist
lass dazu sagen
was für Ergebnisse werden am meisten
wahrscheinlich generiert
um gegeben für jede Kombination von Zuständen
um so gegeben ist der Wert von jedem von jedem uh
Aktiver Faktor um und und das sind Dinge
die sind
dabei entstehen, die man im experimentellen Design bedenken muss
Okay, also die Wahrscheinlichkeit, dass ein
Das Gerät würde die Maschine ausgeben
ein Gewinnschein oder ist das etwas ich
sollte man als die
empirische Person, die mein Experiment entwirft
richtig
ja, genau, also ich zeige dir.
Hier aber richtig, typischerweise kannst du...
Mach es auf andere Weisen, aber typischerweise
dieses Wahrscheinlichkeits-Ding ist das, was es wäre
definiere die um die Belohnungswahrscheinlichkeiten
Okay, man sagt ja, wenn ich bin...
Der gegenwärtige Zustand
„du weißt ja, nachdem man sich für die linke Wahl entschieden hat
uh Slot Machine um, das generiert
Belohnung der Belohnungsbeobachtung mit 0,8
und die nicht Belohnung-Beobachtung als Punkt
als 0,2
zum Beispiel wie zum Beispiel die Belohnung sagen
Die Wahrscheinlichkeit liegt bei 80 Prozent
und Sie wissen, dass der Agent es tun würde
Wenn du möchtest, dass sie diese Wörter lernen.
Wahrscheinlichkeiten, dann würdest du eine von…
Diese kleinen a-Dinge und dann würdest du
Es hat sich ergeben
lerne es um wiederholte Beobachtungen
um
Es ist so kritisch und wirklich.
faszinierender Punkt, das
Die Belohnung fehlt dem Modell nicht.
durch den Präferenzvektor c
Es ist in die Berechnung der Politik eingebettet.
und so ist es, als würde der Agent verfolgen
Präzision
Alles andere gleich durch natürlich
Die Auswahl, die du kennst
Un erfolgreiche Modelle gehen einfach nicht «Active Inference Institute», «Active Inference», «pymdp», «Youtube», «YouTube», «Discord», «GitHub», «ActiveInferenceInstitute», «ActiveInference».
um zu existieren und Modelle, die
sie selbst als Verhalten ausführen sehen
werden nicht lange aktiv sein.
unter einem Modell eines erfolgreichen
Bevorzugung dann gibt es einfach nur ein
Konvergenz in diese Richtung mit allem was da ist
Die Möglichkeiten liegen bereit.
das ist wirklich eine interessante Art, es zu tun
schau, wie re
uhr verstärkungslern-Situationen
kann angepasst werden
die atm-maschinen, manche davon, ein bisschen davon wird benutzt
einen kleinen Tick mehr in der Richtung von
freie Energie Philosophie Sachen aber aber
Ich meine ja, wie die Annahme ist
Die Leute erben Präferenzen, die bestehen bleiben.
Sie am Leben erhalten
um aber äh aber so in der Art wie ein
empirische Aufgabenkontext, den Sie gerade verwenden
c-Vektor zu einfach
definiere, was als Belohnung zählt.
Du weißt schon, es könnte sein, es könnte sein.
etwas richtig es könnte gewinnen Geld
es könnte gewonnen sein
auch wenn es dir kein Geld gibt
Es könnte so sein, wie…
siehst du ein positives Bild, das du kennst
irgendwas in diese Richtung definierst du?
was die Präferenzverteilung ist
und dann parametrisierst du es normalerweise auch
du
passe dies als Parameter an, um zu sehen
im Wesentlichen, wie viel kostet die Person?
gern ausgedrückt
Sie wissen, zwei Dollar zu gewinnen beispielsweise.
um
und ich zeige dir das gleich in einem zweiten
aber ähm ja, ja
so so du brauchst da eine c uh
c-Matrix für jeden so brauchst du einen
Matrix und eine C-Matrix für jede Ausgabe
Modalität
um und du brauchst einen d-Vektor
und mindestens eine V-Matrix für jeden Zustand
Faktor
um als die zu antworten auf deine uh den ursprünglichen
Frage
so wie das erste hier
Das ist du der erste, so dass die Art...
Ich habe beschlossen, das Modell dafür zu bauen.
Die Aufgabe ist
der erste verborgene Zustandsfaktor ist der
Kontext
Okay, bin ich dann im Zustand, dass die...
Der eine ist besser
Ist da jemand im Zustand, wo die richtige Wahl getroffen wird?
ist besser
und ich habe das so begonnen, dies zu spezifizieren
kleines d hier Ding
und die Klammern sagen nur die Zahl
des Zustandsfaktors, das ist d
für Zustandsfaktor-Vorläufe über Zustände für
Zustandsfaktor eins
und es gibt zwei verschiedene mögliche
Zustände besser oder besser schreiben
und ich habe diese gerade als zwei wirklich angegeben
kleine Zahlen
das nur sagt, es sei eine Gleichverteilung
dass es das linke sein wird
das richtige ist besser
aber diese sind wirklich klein und deshalb bin ich
überhaupt nicht zuversichtlich
über Sie wissen, ob diese Verteilung
ist richtig
und ich erkläre dir mehr dazu, wenn
Wir kommen zum Lernen
weil das so ist, wird es weich sein
maximal
um während der Inferenz, damit dies wird
0.5.5
während der Inferenz, aber wenn du lernst du
eher
Erhöhen Sie die Zahlen hier, damit sie werden
Größere Zahlen
was bedeutet, dass der Agent lernt, mehr zu sein
zuversichtlich, was die Verteilung ist
dass es glaubt
aber dann kann ich auch "big d" angeben
was der generativen Prozess ist
und ich habe das als eins und null gesetzt
das bedeutet, dass der wahre Kontext ist
das linke ist besser
damit ist es, was ich dafür verwenden würde
die Priors für den Zustand Faktor eins
um den State-Faktor zwei hier, wenn Sie können
schauen
am Fuss also
Warte mal, schaut ihr das auch?
könnt ihr unten sehen oder?
„äh
für mich kann ich sehen wie mein unterteil die
gern ausgedrückt
Wir sehen nur eine Codezeile ja die d2
bind ja ich frage nur, siehst du?
wie das, suche hier und überall
das Zeug
Es ist perfekt, es ist perfekt, okay jetzt.
Es ist erledigt.
So so dann ist d2 die zweite
verborgenes Zustandsfaktor und das ist der eine
das entspricht deinen Entscheidungen
Okay, das ist hier eine, was bedeutet das?
Es beginnt immer damit, dass
beginnt, dass die erste Spalte hier ist
der Ausgangszustand
und dann kann es entweder in übergehen zu
der Hinweis-Zustand, der zweite
Hier bin ich, ich definiere das.
und dann ist die dritte, das wählen
die linke
Spielautomat-Zustand und der vierte ist
wähle den richtigen Spielautomat-Zustand
das sagt nur zu einem Zeitpunkt, mein
Präferenz
bin mit 100 Prozent Sicherheit, dass ich es werde
beginne mit beginn und nimm
von der Aufgabe, damit das eigentlich ziemlich ist
einfach
Okay, dann ist die nächste Sache...
du musst tun, dass du...
geben Sie die Wahrscheinlichkeit an, sodass eine Matrix
und ich werde dir nicht zeigen, dass
vollendet du eines noch, bevor wir in die
Ich zeige dir den Code, der ich gerade anstelle.
Die wichtigen Teile
um aber so für den zweiten Zustandsfaktor
also, so, für das zweite Ergebnis
Modalität
so die Wahrscheinlichkeitszuordnung für eine Zwei
es wird dieses Ding sein, wo
die erste Zeile entspricht Null, welche
es ist einfach, dass es noch nicht gewonnen hat
oder verloren ist die zweite Reihe das
die Beobachtung, dass es verloren hat
und die dritte Zeile ist die Beobachtung
dass es das ist
und jeder der Spalten hier entspricht
zu
die Zustandsfaktorkonstanten so links
Die Spalte entspricht dem.
das d1 weißt du, dieses Ding, das du kennst
„Also ist der Wert von 0,25 hier für links besser für
der bessere linke Zustand
und der richtige hier ist der, der
entspricht dem besseren Zustand des Lichts
was auf Spalte zwei hier abfällt, so dass die
auf die Weise, wie Sie diese Matrix lesen würden
wenn du dich in dem richtigen Zustand wärst
das ist besser
Dann würdest du zustimmen.
Gewinnen Sie mit dieser Wahrscheinlichkeit
und du würdest mit dieser Wahrscheinlichkeit verlieren
Wenn oder wenn Sie sich in der linken wären
Sie würden mit dieser Wahrscheinlichkeit verlieren und
gewinne mit dieser Wahrscheinlichkeit
um die Spalten dieses weich maximierten
Sind das sind diese Verteilungen ja?
die Spalten sind maximal ausgefüllt
ja, nochmals wenn du meine aussagen meinst
ein wenig technisch, wenn Sie es verwenden
wenn du 'a' als kleines verwendest, sind das".
Dirichlet-Verteilungen
dann werden die Zählungen sich aufbauen, richtig?
Diese Zahlen könnten wie werden
Du weißt, wie etwa 50 25 8 du weißt was immer.
aber diejenigen, die das Vertrauen in kodieren
die Verteilungen aber ja, sie werden
Softmax für die Inferenz
so dann
Also müsste man dann auch «c» angeben
Matrix
für diesen Zustandsfaktor oder ich meine dafür
Ergebnismodalität tut mir leid wegen c2
wird sich im Wesentlichen auf a2 beziehen
Es ist für den Moment, als beide dafür sind.
zweite Ausgabemodalität
und hier erneut Zeilen werden zu sein
Beobachtungen
aber hier die äh die Zeilen entsprechen
Zeitpunkte
im Prozess, um so grundsätzlich gesehen ist
sag es einfach
das um zur Zeit 0 oder zur Zeit 1
Ich habe keine Präferenz für irgendetwas.
Zeit
Ich habe eine negative Präferenz.
das Verlieren
und ich habe eine positive Präferenz für
gewinnen und diese rs-sache ist nur ein
Parameter richtig, so können wir sagen das la
Ding so Verlust der Version
ist jemand, der nicht verlieren möchte
negativ eins
richtig um und für rs sagen rs gleich
vier
das, was man sich als die vier vorstellen kann
Dollarricht
und dann so, wenn es sich beobachtet
gewinnen
zu etwa Zeit zwei wird es vorziehen, dass
mit einem Wert von vier
und wenn es dann zur Zeit drei passiert
es wird rs durch zwei sein
bedeutet es zu Punkt drei, wenn es es hat
nur zwei Dollar gewinnen.
entweder oder was auch immer die relativen Werte
sind für die Person, mit der Sie passen könnten
für eine Person, um zu sehen, wie viel
Sie
Bevorzuge lieber vier Dollar gegenüber zwei, zum Beispiel.
um
und um diese auch um im Code sind
Soft maximiert und dann
„uh, protokolliert, damit sie werden, sie werden
lange Wahrscheinlichkeiten
sozusagen
wie sehr du es hasst zu verlieren und wie viel
Du willst gewinnen
und wieder können Sie diese als festlegen
Parameter
dann für den Zustandsausgang
für das Ausgabemodell, welches ist die
den richtigen Hinweis zu verstehen, dann kannst du keinen
Der Hinweis
Sie können den Hinweis erhalten, dass die linke
Die Maschine ist besser und der Hinweis, dass die
Das richtige Gerät ist besser, richtig, also diejenigen.
sind beide Beobachtungen
und dann kannst du sagen uh mit diesem pha
das ist im Grunde etwas, das man sagen kann
wie informativ ist der Hinweis etwa
Wenn ich die Maschine beobachte
„das deutet an, dass
Gewissheit, dass die linke besser ist oder
Erzählt es mir einfach mit manchen
Die Wahrscheinlichkeit, dass es das bessere ist.
und hier könntest du das einfach so einstellen
„uh, die Sache
du weißt, wie man das einfach nur einstellen kann
ist wie Einsen und Nullen
um einfach nur zu sagen uh
im Wesentlichen würde es einfach sagen, äh wenn pha
das wäre dann einfach nur so eine Aussage
das äh
das Ding ist zu hundert Prozent äh
präzise
um Ihnen zu sagen, welches davon besser ist, wenn
Sie beobachten einen Treffer im Vergleich zu einem anderen.
um und um
und so dann ist die nächste Sache nämlich du
Es muss die möglichen Aktionen berücksichtigt werden
oder Sequenzen von Handlungen, die sich abspielen
um Richtlinien zu entsprechen
und so hier ist die Art, darüber nachzudenken
„das machst du jetzt also
in Zustand eins zuerst Faktor zwei richtig
die ähnliche Handlung
Zustandsfaktor und Sie können entweder
beginnen Sie sofort mit dem Ausgangszustand
choosing the right
machine or you can go immediately from
the start to choosing the left machine
or you can choose to take the hint and
then go to the left one or to the right
one or take the hint and then go to the
left one
so those are like the the those
sequences of actions are the policies
that are gonna
matter right they're gonna encode what
the agent can do
um and so to do that you have to set up
different transition matrices different
b matrices
that encode each of these actions right
transitioning from one
to four transitioning from one to three
transitioning from one to two
transitioning from two to four and two
to three um
and so that's going to correspond to
these setting up these b matrices
which um here so b1
right which is the state factor for uh
the um
which one is which slot machine is
better um
this is just going to be an identity
matrix which basically just says
that the left better context is constant
across the trial
you know it's not as if from time point
one to time point two
the context is gonna change or something
like that right this just says the
belief is
and it is true that each trial has a
stable identity as being the left better
one or the right better one
um but for state factor two so
b2 here that's where you want the agent
to have different possible actions
right so b2 colon colon one
right so the third dimension being the
different uh different possible action
um the first one would be like this
which basically just says so columns
are states at time t
and rows are states at time t plus one
um so this just says i can start in any
state
so in any column and choose to move to
state one this one says i can start in
any column
and move to state two so taking the hint
this one says i can start in any column
so any state and move to
state three which is using the left
machine then same thing here for
changing the
to moving to the right machine so there
are four actions one two three and four
they correspond to four different third
dimensions
in the b matrix for state factor two
um and so then given those
um given those
we specify v which are the policies
um and here the third dimension
corresponds to
which state factor so for this one for
state factor one
there are no actions right it's just
this one v matrix and its identity
matrix
and here the rows are the action and the
columns are
sorry the rows are the time point and
the columns are the uh
the action or the policy sorry
um and so the row here just means action
moving from time one to time two
and the uh um and this second row
means the action from time to time three
um and so that
is useless right for state factor one
because there's just only one action
whereas for state factor two we have all
the different possible action sequences
right so policy one would just be if the
thing just decided to stay in the start
state the whole time right like to just
not do the trial um the other one would
be action two which is take the hint
and then and then take action three
which is move to the
left slot machine or take the hint
it to the third column take the hint and
then move to four which is the action of
choosing the right slot machine
um and then here this is just kind of a
little bit of a trick
but you can choose to at time from one
time to one to time two you can
immediately choose the left slot machine
and then move back to the start state so
three and then one
or same thing choose the right slot
machine and then again move back to
state one
and the only reason for that move back
to state one thing is is that um
if you let the thing stay in state three
and state four
then it's as if it won four dollars and
then won two dollars after that
so you have to kind of move it back out
of the state where it would win
um so so then
you know then you've built everything
really um
so you and you throw all of it in this
little mdp
structure um so i didn't mention this
but you have to specify
t which is the number of time points in
the trial so in this case it would be
uh three um so start take the hint
choose left
start take the hinge who's right et
cetera so there's three time points
um v is just v which is what we defined
um we'll ignore u for now but that's
what you would use if you wanted to
specify one step policies instead but
the thing doesn't look ahead at all um
you know and then a b c and d are just
the different matrices we specified and
we want it to learn
d um so we specify the little d um
and then these other things are just
different parameters that you can set
um so edda is the as a learning rate um
alpha is kind of like an action
precision so it's basically an inverse
temperature parameter it controls how
random someone's
choices are given the policy that they
choose um
beta is the expected free energy
precision that we talked about
and um these other two parameters i
won't really go into detail but they
just have to do with specifying
um the time constant so basically how
quickly evidence accumulates
after an observation and this erp thing
is um
basically it controls it controls
certain assumptions about
what ought to happen if you would make a
new observation each time with respect
to what sorts of
neural responses you would get um
and this is all explained in the code
but i think that's a
it's a perfect pause point so that we
can close within the hour
and leave people with excitement for
part two so
what can they look forward to in part
two and beyond in a minute
yeah so i mean i would just say that you
know once once you have this set up
then the next steps are to run this
structure through
this vbx underscore tutorial script and
that will actually run the model
and you know simulate the behavior the
neural responses and then we'll show you
how to
use um plotting scripts
to display and show how that behavior
show the behavior that uh was the
outcome of the simulation
and then we'll show you how the the kind
of structure the mdp structure works
um and then actually show you some
simulation results and how they work and
things like that
well and i actually probably walk you
through some of the actual code
um that was an amazing session
ryan christopher max thanks so much for
coming on
everybody who was watching live and in
replay also
very appreciated so please leave a
comment
if you have a question or feedback for
the authors or for anyone else
and stay in touch with us because we're
going to be making this a multi-part
series where we're going to be going
deeper into the technical aspects
and also highlighting use cases hearing
about people who are just learning
programming learning to apply it people
who are experts in other fields so
whatever your perspective is you're in
the right spot to be learning
so thanks again all of you for coming on
and we will see you another time